<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ignacio D. Lopez-Miguel</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/</link><atom:link href="https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Ignacio D. Lopez-Miguel</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/media/icon_hu7c08691dc8dbdd8a44d0119594fadcbe_280951_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Ignacio D. Lopez-Miguel</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/</link></image><item><title>Formal Verification of PLCs as a Service: A CERN-GSI Safety-Critical Case Study</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/formal-verification-of-plcs-as-a-service-a-cern-gsi-safety-critical-case-study/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/formal-verification-of-plcs-as-a-service-a-cern-gsi-safety-critical-case-study/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Paper accepted at the NASA Formal Methods Symposium</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/nfm25/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/nfm25/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The increased technological complexity and demand for software reliability require organizations to formally design and verify their safety-critical programs to minimize systematic failures. Formal methods are recommended by functional safety standards (e.g., by IEC 61511 for the process industry and by the generic IEC 61508) and play a crucial role. Their structured approach reduces ambiguity in system requirements, facilitating early error detection. This paper introduces a formal verification service for PLC (programmable logic controller) programs compliant with functional safety standards, providing external expertise to organizations while eliminating the need for extensive internal training. It offers a cost-effective solution to meet the rising demands for formal verification processes. The approach is extended to include modeling time-dependent, know-how-protected components, enabling formal verification of real safety-critical applications. A case study shows the application of PLC formal verification as a service provided by CERN in a safety-critical installation at the GSI particle accelerator facility.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="see-you-in-williamsburg-va">See you in Williamsburg, VA!&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>Student Research Abstract: Enhancing Safety in Cyber-Physical Systems Through Runtime Enforcement</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/student-research-abstract-enhancing-safety-in-cyber-physical-systems-through-runtime-enforcement/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 07:41:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/student-research-abstract-enhancing-safety-in-cyber-physical-systems-through-runtime-enforcement/</guid><description/></item><item><title>3rd prize at the competition of the Symposium on Applied Computing</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/sac24/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/sac24/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The verification and safety assurance of cyber-physical systems pose significant challenges, necessitating innovative solutions for their deployment. Machine Learning (ML) has gained prominence for its diverse applications, particularly in autonomous systems. Despite its potential, the integration of ML into safety-critical domains is met with caution due to multiple concerns. This paper introduces a monitoring system capable of predicting and mitigating requirement violations, featuring a discretized mathematical model for predictions. This monitor includes a decision mechanism to transit between high-assurance and high-performance controllers within a simplex architecture depending on the state of the system. This paper shows an example of how the suggested monitor is able to avoid a property violation by predicting it in advance. These advancements hold promise for enhancing the safety and reliability of cyber-physical systems in safety-critical applications.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Working Together for Safer Systems: A Collaboration Model for Verification of PLC Code</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/working-together-for-safer-systems-a-collaboration-model-for-verification-of-plc-code/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 14:26:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/working-together-for-safer-systems-a-collaboration-model-for-verification-of-plc-code/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Progression for Monitoring in Temporal ASP</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/progression-for-monitoring-in-temporal-asp/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 13:50:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/progression-for-monitoring-in-temporal-asp/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Paper accepted at the European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI)</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/ecai23/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/ecai23/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In recent years, there has been growing interest in the application of temporal reasoning approaches and non-monotonic logics from artificial intelligence in dynamic systems that generate data.
A well-known approach to temporal reasoning is the use of a progression technique, which allows for the online computation of logical consequences of a logical knowledge base over time. We consider
a progression technique for Temporal Here and There and Temporal Equilibrium Logic, which is the logic underlying answer programming over linear-temporal logic (LTL). Compared to usual LTL online computation,
where the goal is to check whether a trace is compliant with a temporal specification, our approach provides also the means to compute non-monotonic temporal reasoning over a trace of
observations. Besides formal notions and results, we also present an algorithm for performing progression to monitor a dynamic system, which has been implemented as a proof of concept and allows for
handling expressive application scenarios.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>From Natural Language Requirements to the Verification of Programmable Logic Controllers: Integrating FRET into PLCverif</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/from-natural-language-requirements-to-the-verification-of-programmable-logic-controllers/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 13:32:54 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/from-natural-language-requirements-to-the-verification-of-programmable-logic-controllers/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Verification of Neural Networks Meets PLC Code: An LHC Cooling Tower Control System at CERN</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/verification-of-neural-networks-meets-plc-code-an-lhc-cooling-tower-control-system-at-cern/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2023 13:26:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/verification-of-neural-networks-meets-plc-code-an-lhc-cooling-tower-control-system-at-cern/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Stop at red? Engineering meets ethics</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/stop-at-red-engineering-meets-ethics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 13:37:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/stop-at-red-engineering-meets-ethics/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Paper accepted at the Engineering Applications of Neural Networks conference</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/eann23/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/eann23/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the last few years, control engineers have started to use artificial neural networks (NNs) embedded in advanced feedback control algorithms. Its natural integration into existing controllers, such as programmable logic controllers (PLCs) or close to them, represents a challenge.
Besides, the application of these algorithms in critical applications still raises concerns among control engineers due to the lack of safety guarantees.
Building trustworthy NNs is still a challenge and their verification is attracting more attention nowadays.
This paper discusses the peculiarities of formal verification of NNs controllers running on PLCs. It outlines a set of properties that should be satisfied by a NN that is intended to be deployed in a critical high-availability installation at CERN. It compares different methods to verify this NN and sketches our future research directions to find a safe NN.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Paper accepted at the NASA Formal Methods Symposium</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/nfm23/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/news/nfm23/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>PLCverif is an actively developed project at CERN, enabling the formal verification of Programmable Logic Controller (PLC) programs in critical systems. In this paper, we present our work on improving the formal requirements specification experience in PLCverif through the use of natural language. To this end, we integrate NASA’s FRET, a formal requirement elicitation and authoring tool, into PLCverif. FRET is used to specify formal requirements in structured natural language, which automatically translates into temporal logic formulae. FRET’s output is then directly used by PLCverif for verification purposes. We discuss practical challenges that PLCverif users face when authoring requirements and the FRET features that help alleviate these problems. We present the new requirement formalization workflow and report our experience using it on two critical CERN case studies.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="see-you-in-houston">See you in Houston!&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>Simplification of numeric variables for PLC model checking</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/simplification-of-numeric-variables-for-plc-model-checking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 22:24:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/simplification-of-numeric-variables-for-plc-model-checking/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Applying Model Checking to Highly-Configurable Safety Critical Software: The SPS-PPS PLC Program</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/applying-model-checking-to-highly-configurable-safety-critical-software-the-sps-pps-plc-program/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 20:20:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/applying-model-checking-to-highly-configurable-safety-critical-software-the-sps-pps-plc-program/</guid><description/></item><item><title>PLCverif: Status of a Formal Verification Tool for Programmable Logic Controller</title><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/plcverif-status-of-a-formal-verification-tool-for-programmable-logic-controller/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 19:49:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/publication/plcverif-status-of-a-formal-verification-tool-for-programmable-logic-controller/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/admin/config.yml</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ignaciolopezmiguel.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>